Guide to the Seema Weatherwax photographs M0868
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Seema Weatherwax photographs
1933-1993
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Weatherwax, Seema, 1905-2006
M0868
3 linear ft.
3 box(es)
Seema Aissen Weatherwax was a photographer and social activist who was part of the Film and Photo League, worked with Ansel Adams in Yosemite, and shot Woody Guthrie and migrant workers at a California FSA camp. Collection contains prints and negatives, as well as an original typescript by her husband John Weatherwax.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography / Administrative History
Emigrating from Tsarist Russia with her parents in 1913 to escape persecution and the conscription act, Seema Aissen graduated from high school and began studying science courses in Leeds, England. A few years after her father's death, her mother took the three daughters to Boston to join relatives, and Seema became involved in photography. She moved to Southern California in 1929, lived in Tahiti for a year, and upon returning to Los Angeles joined the Film and Photo League in 1934. Ansel Adams asked her to run his darkroom in Yosemite in 1938. The following year she assisted Adams with the first Camera Workshop in Yosemite. In 1941 Seema met the writer Jack Weatherwax, and together with folk singer Woody Guthrie visited the Shafter Farm Security Administration Camp, managed by noted civil rights advocate Fred Ross. At Shafter she photographed Dust Bowl refugees and their surroundings. The Weatherwaxes moved to Santa Cruz, California in 1984. Following the death of her husband, Seema continued her activism, including working with the NAACP and the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, and at the age of 95 organized the first exhibition of her work. She passed away in 2006, two months shy of her 101st birthday.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection contains prints and and negatives of the 1933 Long Beach earthquake (commercial prints not by Weatherwax); Woodie Guthrie, Fred Ross, and the Shafter farm labor camp, 1941; a Los Angeles labor demonstration, 1945; the Hollywood strike, 1945; and many formal and informal photographs from the Yosemite camera workshops with Ansel Adams and Edward Weston, 1941-1942. Also included is a 24-page typescript, "The Queen of Montgomery Street," by her husband, John M. Weatherwax.
Related Materials
University of California, Santa Cruz also holds a collection on Seema Weatherwax. The Archives of American Art holds a collection of John Weatherwax papers related to Rivera and Kahlo.
Agricultural laborers--California.; Demonstrations--California.; Earthquakes--Long Beach.; Photography.; Shafter (Calif.); Yosemite; Weatherwax, Seema, 1905-2006; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984; Guthrie, Woodie, 1912-1967.; Ross, Fred, 1910-1992; Weatherwax, John M.; Weston, Edward.; Lancelot, Sir; Film and Photo League (U.S.)
- Series 1. Photographs
  - Long Beach Earthquake, 1933 (photographer unknown), 53 photos in 16 sheets (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yosemite, Ansel Adams Camera Workshop, 1938 - 1940; 19 sheets (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Lee Warren, Ansel Adams' secretary, First Camera Workshop, Bests Studio, Yosemite, Seema's Apartment, Party at Studio in Yosemite, Ansel Adams in Yosemite, Seema Weatherwax, Virginia Adams 1993
  - I am an American Day, Los Angeles, 1940 - 1950; 15 sheets (photographs and negatives) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sir Lancelot, Trinidad Performers, 1940 - 1950; 8 sheets (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Demonstrations for Jobs, Los Angeles, 1945; 6 sheets (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hollywood Strike 1945, Shafter Farm Camp Negatives 1941, 22 sheets (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Russian Delegates to the U.N. Conference, 1945; 5 sheets (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shafter Farm Labor Camp, 1941; 4 photographs in 4 sheets (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Shafter Farm Camp, the Californians Magazine [1 of 2], 1941; 14 photographs, 15 sheets (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Shafter Farm Camp, The Californians Magazine [2 of2], 1941; 11 photographs in 11 sheets (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Return to Shafter Farm Camp, 1994, 26 color photographs in 10 sheets (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2. Papers
  - Typed Labels for Shafter Camp Photographs, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes for Filmstrip: El Camino Viejo, nd; 4 typed sheets (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Script for "Who Wants War?Who Wants Peace?"[in English and Spanish], 18 typed sheets (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Negro History filmstrip script, nd; 4 typed sheets (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, U.S. Dept. of Interior, 1983; 2 typed sheets (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Typescript by Jack Weatherwax, "The Queen of Montgomery Street", nd; 24 typed pages (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, various, 61 typed pages (Box 1, Folder 18)
    correspondence re Woody Guthrie photographs, obituaries of Fred Ross, correspondence regarding The Californians article, Biographical sketch of Seema Weatherwax
  - The Californians Magazine (2), 1992, 1993; 2 issues of The Californians Magazine (Box 1, Folder 19)
    typed biographical sketch of Seema WeatherwaxThe Californians, Vol.9 No.4, The Californians, Vol.10, No.4
- Series 3. Matted photographs
  - Portraits, people, 1942 - 1946; 6 matted black and white photographs (Box 2, Folder 1)
    baby in yard, 1944, Ansel Adams, 1946, Lee Warren (2) 1946, Gypsy Mary - Las Vegas, 1942, Old Miner - Las Vegas, 1942
  - Yosemite, High Sierras, 1938 - 1941; 6 black and white matted photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
    High Sierras, Storm Yosemite, Storm Yosemite, 1938, Yosemite, 1940, Yosemite, 1941, High Sierras 11,000 feet, 1946,
  - Nature, Scenes from Train, 1940 - 1946; 4 black and white matted photographs (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Scene from Train, 1946, Scene from Back of Train, 1946, Untitled, 1940, Monterey, 1946
- Series 4. Audio-visual Materials
  Conditions Governing Access
  The Media materials require at least two weeks advance notice to use in order to allow staff time to have use copies made from the original items.
  - El Taller de Grafica Popular, nd; 1 filmstrip (Box 3, Othertype 1)
  - California's Gold, nd; video (Box 3, Othertype 1)
    Episode #601, "Weed Patch"
  - Taller de Grafica Popular, 1996; video (Box 3, Othertype 2)
    Taller de Grafica Popular, Who Wants War, Who Wants Peace